<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/esr2html.xsl"?>

<ESR xmlns="http://common-criteria.rhcloud.com/ns/esr" name="Server Virtualization">

	<intro>
		<esrtitle>Server Virtualization Essential Security Requirements</esrtitle>
		<maintainer>National Information Assurance Partnership</maintainer>
		<identifier>42</identifier>
		<version>1.0</version>
		<status>final</status>
		<issuedate>19 October 2016</issuedate>
		<approver/>
		<supercedes/>
	</intro>
	
	<section title="Status" id="status">
		This Essential Security Requirements (ESR) document specifies the essential 
		requirements for server virtualization software. 
	</section>

	<section title="Background and Purpose" id="purpose">
		<!-- This section sets the context for not only the ESR, but what is 
			expected of the resulting Protection Profile (PP). The intent is 
			that the remaining sections provide succinct statements that 
			highlight the relevant aspects to be addressed by the Technical 
			Community (TC) constructing the PP. Here, the authors provide a 
			narrative that introduces the reader to the problem being solved, 
			and presents key aspects that support or guide the TC, and may
			elaborate on subtleties not apparent in the “bulleted” high level
			statements.
		-->
		Server Virtualization, for the purposes of this EP, refers to a virtualization 
		system (VS) that implements virtualized hardware components on server-class hardware. 
		It creates a virtualized hardware environment for each instance of a guest operating 
		system (virtual machines or VMs) permitting these environments to execute concurrently 
		while maintaining isolation and the appearance of exclusive control over assigned computing 
		resources. Each VM instance supports applications such as file servers, web servers, 
		and mail servers. Server virtualization may also support client operating systems in a 
		virtual desktop or thin-client environment. Typically, virtualized servers provide services 
		to remote clients and are generally not directly accessible by non-administrative users.<br></br>

		This EP does not address client virtualization, application virtualization, or containers.
	</section>

	<section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">
		<!-- 
			This section is intended to provide the initial scope/bound of the 
			security problem by providing the reader with concise statements 
			regarding the scenarios in which the technology is being used. The 
			intended usage presented here should lay the groundwork for the 
			identifying the resources to be protected, and what threats must be
			considered in the drafting of the Essential Security Requirements 
			(ESR) and for the TC to consider when writing the PP.
		-->
		<ul>
			<li>Virtualized Servers – Virtualized instances of network services traditionally 
				executed on separate hardware platforms, such as web servers, file servers, and 
				mail servers. 
			</li>
			<li>Virtualized Network Infrastructure – Virtualized instances of routers, switches, 
				and other network infrastructure. 
			</li>
			<li>Virtualized Enterprise User Environments – The server back-end of virtual 
				desktop (VDI) or thin-client implementations where actual computation occurs 
				in a server-based VM and the user interacts through a client. The client 
				application is not covered by this EP.
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Resources to be protected" id="resourcesprotected">
		<!-- 
    		This section is intended to provide the initial scope/bound of the 
    		security problem by providing the reader with concise statements
    		regarding the scenarios in which the technology is being used. The 
    		intended usage presented here should lay the groundwork for the 
    		identifying the resources to be protected, and what threats must be
    		considered in the drafting of the Essential Security Requirements 
    		(ESR) and for the TC to consider when writing the PP.
    	-->
		<ul>
			<li>The platform onto which the Virtualization System is installed including the hardware, 
				firmware, and host operating system
			</li>
			<li>The Virtual Machine Manager (VMM) including the Hypervisor and Service VMs
			</li>
			<li>The Management Subsystem (if applicable)
			</li>
			<li>The VMs and their contents
			</li>
		</ul>		
	</section>

	<section title="Attacker access" id="attackeraccess"> 
		An attacker has access to either:
		<ul>
			<li>One or more Guest VMs, and
			</li>
			<li>Its operational network
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
	
	<section title="TOE Boundary" id="boundary">
		<ul>
			<li>The Virtual Machine Manager (VMM)
				<ul>
					<li>The Hypervisor
					</li>
					<li>Service VMs
					</li>
					<li>VM abstractions (but not Guest VM workloads)
					</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			<li>The Management Subsystem (if applicable)
			</li>
		</ul>	
	</section>

	<section title="Essential Security Requirements" id="requirements">
		<!--
        	This is where the authors present an initial set of English 
        	requirements that specify security functionality, rather than 
        	design and/or implementation characteristics. These requirements 
        	will provide the foundation for which the detailed set of 
        	requirements is derived. It is important that the requirements 
        	captured here make an attempt to fully address the categories 
        	(e.g., access control, identification and authentication, 
        	management capabilities, roles of administration, secure 
        	communications, and audit). That's not to say the requirements are 
        	fully specified or detailed enough to simply translate to Common 
        	Criteria security functional requirements. The goal is that there 
        	is enough information contained here, as well as the other sections
        	of this document, to provide the TC enough information to ensure 
        	they have an understanding of what is minimally required in breath.
        -->
		The following are the essential security requirements that are expected to 
		be implemented by any application that is compliant with the Server Virtualization 
		EP. Note that these security requirements are conditional on that functionality 
		being present. For example, a product that does not require an external network 
		connection for any purpose is considered to satisfy any security requirements that 
		pertain to the secure use of external network connections. 
		<br></br>
		Any other conditional requirements that depend on whether or not the product 
		implements a certain capability are listed in the “Optional Extensions” section below.
		<br></br>
		The Virtualization System shall:
		<ul>
			<li>Maintain isolation between its VMs (and their resources)
			</li>
			<li>Maintain the integrity of the VMM
			</li>
			<li>Protect the platform from VMs and remote users of the VS
			</li>
			<li>Protect the Management Subsystem (if applicable) from unauthorized access
			</li>
			<li>Be capable of being updated/patched in a secure and timely manner
			</li>
			<li>Provide the VMs access to sufficient sources of entropy (or necessary platform resources)
			</li>
			<li>Provide audit capabilities for security-relevant events
			</li>
		</ul>
		
	</section>

	<section title="Assumptions" id="assumptions">
		<!--
			Simply put, this section presents the aspects of the product and 
			its	intended environment that can be assumed to hold true. This 
			will provide additional scope on the resulting PP.
		-->
		<ul>
			<li>The VS relies on a trustworthy computing platform for its execution, and it 
				is assumed that the platform has not been compromised prior to the installation of the VS.
			</li>
			<li>Physical security appropriate to the value of the VS and the data it contains is provided.
			</li>
			<li>Administrators of the VS are trusted follow and apply all Administrator guidance.
			</li>
			<li>The VMs will have assurance sufficient to outweigh the risk that they will violate the 
				security policy of the TOE by using covert channels.
			</li>
			<li>The user of the VS is not willfully negligent or hostile, and uses the VS in compliance 
				with the applied enterprise security policy and guidance.
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>


	<section title="Optional Extensions" id="extensions"> 
		The following requirements may already be realized in some products in this technology class, 
		but the ESR is not mandating these capabilities exist in “baseline” level products:
		<ul>
			<li>Automatic response to certain security events
			</li>
			<li>Verifying VM Integrity
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Objective Requirements" id="objective"> 
		Requirements captured in this section specify security-relevant behavior that is not expected to be 
		realized currently in products of this type, but they are capabilities that may be mandated in future 
		versions of the ESR and resulting PPs. 
		<ul>
			<li>Device Driver Isolation
			</li>
			<li>Support for Software Identification Tags
			</li>
			<li>Support for VM Introspection
			</li>
			<li>Support for Measured Launch of Platform and VMM
			</li>
		</ul>
	</section>

	<section title="Outside the TOE's Scope" id="outsidescope">
		<!--
			This is where the authors explicitly state things they do not want 
			to be considered for inclusion in an evaluation against a 
			resulting PP.  Items expressed here could include threats, 
			functions or capabilities that would require assurance activities 
			that are too subjective, or specific expertise not available in the
			evaluation facilities expected to assess products against the PP 
			(e.g., assessing anti-tamper measures). 
		-->
		<ul>
			<li>The platform onto which the Virtualization System is installed including the hardware, 
				firmware, and non-VS-essential portions of the host operating system (if any)
			</li>
			<li>Software installed inside VMs that is unrelated to the functioning of the Virtualization System
			</li>
			<li>Application virtualization
			</li>
			<li>Containers
			</li>
		</ul>	
	</section>
</ESR>
